Let's consider a one dimensional motion that
has a non-uniform acceleration.
What we'd like to do is explore how
do you differentiate position functions,
to get velocity functions, to get acceleration functions.
So what we're going to consider is a rocket.
So I'm going to choose a coordinate system y.
And here's my rocket.
And I have a function y of t.
And I'll have a j-hat direction, but this will
be a one dimensional motion.
Now I want to express while the rocket is thrusting upwards
and the engine is burning, we can describe a function y of t
to be equal to 1/2 a constant a naught
minus the gravitational acceleration, times t squared.
And we're going to have a separate term here, which
is minus 1 over 30.
And you'll see where this 30 comes in
as we start to differentiate.
The same constant a naught, t to the 1/6 over t naught
to the 1/4.
Now in this expression, a naught is bigger than g.
And also, this is only true, this
holds for the time interval 0 less than
or equal to t, less than t naught.
And at time t equals to t naught, the engine shuts off.
And at that moment, our expectation
will be that the y component of the acceleration
should just be minus g, for t greater than t naught.
So now let's calculate the acceleration
as the velocity and the position as functions of time.
So the velocity-- in each case, we're
going to use the polynomial rule.
So the y component of the velocity
is just the derivative of t squared, which is just 2t.
And so we get a naught minus g times t.
And when we differentiate t at the 1/6, the 6 over 30
gives us factor 1 over 5.
So we have minus 1 over 5 times a naught, t to the 1/5
over t naught to the 1/4.
And this is a combination of a linear term and a term
that is decreasing by this t to the 1/5 factor.
And finally, we now take the next derivative, ay of t,
which is d dy dt.
I'll just keep functions of t, but we don't really need that.
And when we differentiate here, we get a naught minus g.
Now you see the 5s are canceling,
and we have minus a naught t to the 1/4 over t naught
to the 1/4.
Now at time t equals t naught, what do we have?
Well, ay at t equals t naught.
This is just a factor minus a naught.
Those cancel, and we get minus g, which is what we expected.